In this lecture, we'll cover how to build the data path for a simple, single-cycle processor.
At this point, we've gotten through the preview spots we've needed to address before we could
put it all together.
Hopefully, some parts have been reviewed, but fret not if you've been learning more
than you expected.
These are the fundamentals for building a simple processor which will be crucial to
understand for your semester project.
So first, a quick review of sequential logic design concepts, then we'll get into the
components of our single-cycle implementation, which is a processor that executes each instruction
in just one cycle.
Recall that a combinational circuit's output is solely a function of the inputs.
An example is the ALU from the previous lecture.
On the other hand, if a logic circuit has state, it's called sequential, as in its
outputs are dependent not only on its current input signals, but also of internal state
that was set from previous input signals.
To retain state before inputs change, we need to build storage elements to hold our logic
signals.
The most basic form is a latch.
Here is a level-sensitive D latch that is controlled by a clock C, or enable, signal.
When the clock is high, the latch is transparent and the input data D simply passes through
to the output Q.
When the clock is low, the output is locked and the D input can change without modifying
Q.
So how does it work?
When the outputs of the AND gates are zero, the current input Q is retained via the cross-coupled
NOR gates.
Whatever the current value of Q is, it is fed through the bottom NOR gate and inverted,
then fed back up to reinforce the Q value.
This acts like an infinite loop in C, but the wires don't toggle once values of Q and
Q0 are set.
We can compose two of these latches to make a flip-flop, which in this case is officially
called a master-slave D flip-flop.
The idea of a flip-flop is to make the device edge-triggered, that is to say it is opaque
except for the edges of the clock.
How is this edge-triggering accomplished?
In this example, when the clock C is high, the latch on the left is transparent and drives
the value of D to Q, while the latch on the right is locked because it gets inverted clock.
When clock C drops to zero, the leftmost latch locks in Q and the inverted clock makes the
latch on the right transparent, so the value of master Q before the falling edge is now
transmitted to slave Q.
We know that logic gates have delays, and as these delays, they prevent both latches
from momentarily being transparent at the same time.
In a design that uses this negative edge flip-flop, the value of input D can change due to the
cone of logic driving it, and only at the negative edge of the clock will that value
get locked into the flip-flops Q output.
So why do we need flip-flops for creating a processor?
Let's look at this example.
Here we have a D flip-flop that stores a value, then a combinatorial circuit increments it
by one and stores the new value back into the flip-flop.
This incrementer circuit works perfectly when implemented with a flip-flop, however, if we
were to use a latch instead, we would have a problem.
Whenever the clock is high, recall that the latch is transparent, which creates a combinational
loop.
Now we truly have an infinite loop on our hands.
When the latch is open, if the incrementer were fast enough, it could, in theory, increment
several times before the latch became opaque.
It would be impossible to predict what the value it held would be considering per-bit
logic delays through an incrementer.
The professionals all use D flip-flops, and in fact, many Veralog linters will flag inferred
latches as errors.
Like the vast majority of our industry, we will be creating a fully synchronous design.
Our goal is to study the architectural components of a processor, not discover how much trouble
we can get into with timing correctness.
All of the state you will use in your processor are to be implemented using D flip-flops.
It's your choice to determine if you want them to be positive or negative edge triggered,
but positive edge is more common.
As a simplification, all of our design diagrams can omit the clock signals.
All sequential cells will be connected to the same clock, and as Professor Sohi told
me when I took this course, it will be a long time before you are allowed to directly use
a clock as an input.
He was right.
I've yet to directly use a clock as a logic input, though modern synthesis flows will
insert clock gators during synthesis for logic that is not being activated.
And in your implementations, all logic should complete within a cycle, and no combinational
logic should run through multiple cycles and form what's known as a multi-cycle path or
MCP.
Here's our single-cycle data path at a glance.
You'll understand everything here by the end of this lecture.
The processor must first fetch or load an instruction from memory before it can be executed.
Recall that the program counter PC is a special register that points to the current instructions
address and memory.
The PC is stored in a dedicated 32-bit registered, which really is just 32 flip flops, which
you cannot access except indirectly through branch and jump instructions.
We read out the instruction word at the memory location specified by the PC and pass it along.
Ignoring branches and jumps for now, the general procedure is to increment the PC to move on
to the next instruction for the next cycle.
In our MIPS processor we've been studying, every instruction is exactly 4 bytes long,
so we increment the PC by 4 to stay word aligned and write this next value to the PC register.
The fetch component has pushed the instruction to the decode and register file components.
The decoder determines what kind of instruction it is and sets the control bits or busses
like register write and ALU operation.
Note the diagram hints, register write is just a line, so it's one bit.
The ALU operation has a slash through it, indicating it is multiple bits wide.
Let's consider arithmetic and logic instructions first, like the AND instruction shown in this
example.
The MIPS R format has three 5-bit register numbers in it.
The decoder will determine that the AND instruction is an R format, so RS and RT in the instruction
word specify which registers to read.
In this case, they are registers 2 and 3.
All 32-bit MIPS registers are contained in the register file.
We'll discuss its implementation in a later slide.
The input registers are specified via the read register 1 and 2 inputs to the register
file and their values are then read out and fed into the ALU, which performs the AND instruction,
which is, of course, decoded from the opcode and function bits of the instruction word.
The control signal register write is then asserted to enable writing the ALU result
back into the register file.
The decoder has already driven the write register to the value of the instruction field RD,
which is 1 in this case.
In the next lecture, we'll discuss how to implement the control logic that drives the
control signal's ALU operation and register write.
Now let's take a look at memory load and store instructions as specified by the MIPS I format.
The RS input register specifies the base address of the memory location that we will be loading
from or storing to.
This register is read out from the first read port of the register file and fed to the ALU,
where it is added to the immediate offset encoded in the instruction word.
This 16-bit immediate field is signed extended to 32 bits and fed in as the second operand
to the ALU.
The sum of the base input register plus the immediate offset yields the address that will
be accessed in the data memory.
At this point, loads and stores diverge in operation.
Load instructions follow the red data path.
The memory write control signal is de-asserted, so the write data input is ignored.
The memory read control signal is asserted, so after some memory read delay, the data
stored at the address is read out, which then heads to the register file and is written
to the RT register specified in the instruction word.
Store instructions follow the blue data path.
This time, the RT register is an input to the data memory component and needs to be read
out from the register file via the second read port.
This is the value that we are going to write into memory.
The memory write control signal is asserted, and the write data input to the memory is
written to the specified address.
The memory read and register write control signals are both de-asserted during loads.
Now we'll take a look at branch instructions, using branch on equal as an example.
Recall that branches are I-format instructions.
The value of the two input registers are compared, and if they are equal, then the branch
is taken.
Taking a branch simply sets the PC to the relative address specified by the immediate
offset.
Because branch instructions are relative to the next PC, we'll compute the common
case PC plus 4 as usual, and then compute the target PC by shifting and sign extending
the immediate offset and adding it to the result of PC plus 4.
Our processor will use the ALU to subtract the two input register values.
If the result is zero, then the PC is written to the target PC for the next cycle, otherwise
it will just get PC plus 4.
Here's the partial diagram for branch instructions.
At the top, we use another adder to compute the target PC.
The first operand is PC plus 4, which is the output of the adder in the fetch data path
from a few slides ago.
The second operand is the value after the immediate field has been sign extended and
shifted left to.
As planned, we'll reuse the ALU data path to subtract the two input registers to compare.
We augment the ALU with the zero flag, indicating the result of an operation is zero, which
will drive the branch control logic to multiplex either PC plus 4 or branch target to write
the next PC.
In the first lecture, we hinted that an ISA filled with simple but useful instructions
could be composed to solve any problem.
These last few slides have been an example of creating a processor architecture that
has simple but reusable components.
While we see the need to put dedicated adders to compute the next PC, the main ALU continues
to do heavy lifting for all three types of MIPS instructions.
Lastly, let's discuss how to implement the register file.
In our single cycle processor, the maximum number of registers we'll need to access
per instruction will be two for reading and one for writing.
Our register file consists of 32 registers, each 32 bits wide.
Each register is just a row of 32 D flip flops.
Let's start with how to read registers.
Each flip flops Q output is connected to two vertical output bit lines, which correspond
to the read data ports.
Each read data bit line is connected to a tri-state driver, which is controlled by the
corresponding word line from the one hot decoder.
The read register one and two inputs are the five bit register IDs, which then go through
the 32 bit one hot decoders and assert one of the corresponding word lines.
Let's say the read register one input specifies register five, then the fifth word line is
asserted, which activates all of the R1 tri-state drivers along the fifth row of flip flops.
To write a register, each flip flop's D input is connected to the write data input bit line,
and each flip flop's write enable is asserted by the word lines from the topmost one hot
decoder, which decodes the register ID to be written to.
With this organization, we can simultaneously read two registers and write one register
in the same cycle.
Let's put all of these components together to get the simple data path for our single
cycle processor.
Different paths are triggered depending on the instruction we're executing, whether
it's arithmetic load, store, or branch.
So we need muxes to selectively activate different parts.
There are three key muxes shown here.
The first is the ALU source mux, which picks the second ALU operand from either the second
read port of the register file like with our format instructions, or the sign extended
immediate value as seen in load store instructions.
Next is the mem to reg mux, which selects the data to write into the register file,
which could be either the ALU result or the data loaded from memory.
Finally, we have the PC source mux at top, which selects between the next PC or the target
PC depending on whether a branch is to be taken.
In the next lecture, we'll discuss how the wires and buses of the control block generate
all of these signals.
It's time once again to look at a few examples to test our learning.
Suppose a bug in your design leads to the ALU source control signal being stuck at one.
Would this add instruction still function correctly?
As before, please pause the video and work this through.
You'll be doing a lot of debug on your project, so I strongly encourage you to give it a shot
now.
Keep listening if you want a few hints.
As you're thinking about this problem, consider which instruction format is ADD.
Is it R, I, or J?
Look up the opcode and function for ADD.
Look up the register name to get the register number.
Fill in the full 32-bit value in hexadecimal format.
Note that this will involve regrouping these fields into groups of four.
Now for instructions with immediates.
Which bits of the instruction word do these come from?
If ALU source were stuck at one, the ADD would fail.
It would drive the second ALU input to the sign extended lower 16 bits of the instruction
word, since that's where the I format has the field, even though the ADD is an R format
instruction, which does not have an immediate field.
If you didn't understand where the hex 4020 constant comes from, please note that the
bottom 16 bits of our format consist of the RD field, the shift amount field, and the
funct field.
The destination RD is register T0, aka register 8, the shift amount for an ADD is 0, and the
function for an ADD is hex 20.
The value is positive, so sign extension consists of 16 zeros.
Please double check that you understand where this number is coming from.
Alright, same bug, but we're looking at a store instruction this time.
If ALU source is again stuck at one, would this store instruction still work correctly?
You know, maybe this is a bug you'll have on your project, so please take an honest
attempt at working through it after pausing this video.
Turns out store word is unaffected.
Per the MIPS green card, store word is an I format instruction, which uses the immediate
value as an offset to the base address stored in the register specified in the RS field.
A bug free design would have set ALU source to a 1 anyway, so this instruction at least
works correctly.